<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-11-01T10:02:08+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Prashant Kikani</title><subtitle>Prashant Kikani is a data scientist &amp; machine learning enthusiast. His goal is to make a +ve impact on millions of people's daily lives &amp; to be hyper-optimistic about the future.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">A realistic way to live a happy life</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/happy-life" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A realistic way to live a happy life" /><published>2019-09-19T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2019-09-19T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/happy-life</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/happy-life">&lt;p&gt;In this post, I share my ideas to live a happy life by following some simple, realistic &amp;amp; statistically valid ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-uncomfortable-truth&quot;&gt;The Uncomfortable Truth&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;One day, you and everyone you love will die. And beyond a small group of people for an extremely brief period of time, 
little of what you say or do will ever matter. This is the Uncomfortable Truth of life. 
And everything you think or do is but an elaborate avoidance of it. 
We are inconsequential cosmic dust, bumping and milling about on a tiny blue speck. We imagine our own importance. 
&lt;mark&gt;We invent our purpose&lt;/mark&gt; — we are nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what? Should we all give up whatever we are doing as nothing matters anyway? Surely NO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This leads to the idea of &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.becomingminimalist.com/what-is-minimalism/&quot;&gt;minimalism&lt;/a&gt;. We’ll discuss that in a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;why-our-generation-is-so-stressed--unhappy&quot;&gt;Why our generation is so stressed &amp;amp; unhappy?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of modern technology &amp;amp; social media, we have became habitual of instant gratification. We give damn about almost everything that is not in our control. Therefor we tie our happiness with stuff which we can’t control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, People care about who wins IPL, how many followers their friends have, why people don’t reply instantly on WhatsApp, why people love/hate Modi etc. We can’t control these things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does that mean we shouldn’t care about anything? Become a saint? Again, surely NO. Then what should we do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;solution-10&quot;&gt;Solution 1.0&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solution is simple. Give your damn to only 4–5 things. Like your goals, career, family &amp;amp; very close friends, your idols. That’s it. It’s that simple. Why you need to care about other things when you have limited amount of days to live?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, only care about things which you can control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That does not mean to be cruel to other people/thing you don’t care about. Be kind; but up to a certain limit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do this, you &amp;amp; only you have your key to happiness. As your future lies in your hands. If you do well, you achieve your goals, become happy. If you don’t do well, you fail, you try again with different approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-trap&quot;&gt;The Trap&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does that mean, once you achieve a goal you become happy? No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You become more eager to achieve the next one. There’s nothing wrong with expecting more. But it’s an endless loop. &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.foxnews.com/travel/top-10-secrets-casinos-dont-want-you-to-know&quot;&gt;Casinos&lt;/a&gt; in Las Vegas run on this simple human behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what’s the solution now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;satisfaction&quot;&gt;Satisfaction&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to be satisfied with what you have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now does that mean we should never expect more? In that way, humanity will never achieve higher standards. No.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing is, we attach our selves &amp;amp; our own happiness with that expectation (or goals). If we fail to achieve that for some reason, we’ll again feel sad no matter how much we have already. We are giving our key to happiness to something else. So, what to do now?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;solution-20&quot;&gt;Solution 2.0&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, with what we should attach our happiness? The process. That’s the only thing we can control. Achieving that goal also have other factors which you can’t control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost all things (or your goals) follow this simple realistic fact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Outcome = Result of ( Things you can control + Things you can’t control )
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That outcome can be anything. Your goal or something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, you want to reach to bus station on time. Thing you can control is, leaving 20 minutes earlier from home. Things you can’t control are puncture in car, huge traffic jam etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you attach your happiness with LHS of the equation, you may or may not be happy as there are factors you can’t control. But if you attach happiness with 1st part of RHS, you’ll always be happy as only you control it. You gave your 100% or not? If yes, then no worries. If no, try again next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Idea of minimalism also works here. Steve Jobs have applied this in his life successfully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;one-more-thing&quot;&gt;One more thing&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t lie to yourself. Don’t pretend that, I always give my best then also I almost never achieve my goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Statistically speaking, if you gave your best in 10 shots and only 1–2 worked out, there’s high probability that something wrong is going on with so called “your best”. Assuming things you can’t control (i.e. 2nd part of the equation), follow the &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Normal_distribution&quot;&gt;normal distribution&lt;/a&gt;, theoretically, your success rate should be more than 49% if you always gave your best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be realistic. No one is perfect. You need to constantly improve yourself by learning more &amp;amp; more till your last breath. Almost no one can achieve goals (and become “happy”) in short time. Exceptions are always there. But ignoring those outliers, you need to do a lot of practice to become master at something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real world don’t give instant gratification as modern technology &amp;amp; social media give.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-thought-on-comparison&quot;&gt;A thought on Comparison&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People say, don’t compare yourself with others, you’ll end up sad. That’s not true. Comparison is not bad. Unhealthy comparison is bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Messi is getting better everyday because of Ronaldo; Ronaldo is getting better everyday because of Messi. Same is true for Google &amp;amp; Microsoft, Pepsi &amp;amp; Coca-cola, Adidas &amp;amp; Nike. They do healthy comparison. If they can do it better why can’t we?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they know the limit. They don’t attach themselves with outcome. If they do, they will burn out soon. They accept the result &amp;amp; learn from it. So, do healthy comparison if want to get better in long term. Healthy comparison is a win-win condition. Both party get better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-solution&quot;&gt;The solution&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be happy in long term,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Give your damns to things only you can control &amp;amp; don’t lie to yourself. Be realistic &amp;amp; optimistic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FYI, If you have food, cloths &amp;amp; a home to live, you are already far more happier than billions of people in the world. Think this way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the evolution of mankind, 100 billion human beings have walked the Earth. If you are reading this, you are likely in the top 1% by any measure: opportunity, security, happiness. In fact, you might be in the top 0.1% or even 0.01%. What an amazing opportunity. You’re truly among the blessed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happiness is all that matters at the end of the day. Have a happy life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;👏 👏 You made it till the end ! Congrats.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Prashant Kikani</name></author><summary type="html">In this post, I share my ideas to live a happy life by following some simple, realistic &amp;amp; statistically valid ways.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What I learned from my 7 month ML journey</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/7-month-ml-journey" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What I learned from my 7 month ML journey" /><published>2018-05-14T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2018-05-14T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/7-month-ML-journey</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/7-month-ml-journey">&lt;p&gt;This little post is about what I have learned from my 7 month ML journey. Hope a newbie like me found something to invest his/her 5 minutes in this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About 7 months ago, I seriously started to focus in ML field. And right now, I have done many considerable good things. I have done projects like &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/prashant-kikani/toxic-comment-classifier&quot;&gt;toxic-comment-classifier&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/prashant-kikani/sarcasm-detector-by-CNN&quot;&gt;sarcasm-detector&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/prashant-kikani/movie-recommender&quot;&gt;movie-recommender&lt;/a&gt; etc. And some “non-ML” projects like &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://github.com/prashant-kikani/image-optimizer&quot;&gt;image-optimizer&lt;/a&gt; and an online gaming site to play Tic-Tac-Toe against unbeatable bot. Also I am an &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.kaggle.com/prashantkikani&quot;&gt;expert&lt;/a&gt; in Kaggle kernels and doing summer Internship in Deep learning in Bangalore, India.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will divide this post in &lt;b&gt;3 parts&lt;/b&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to start?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to grow?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to maintain?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-to-start-in-ml&quot;&gt;How to start in ML?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This question is very common in almost all of the aspirants. One basic analogy is, one needs to have at least basic knowledge of statistics, calculus (specially for Deep Learning) and linear algebra to understand concepts of Machine Learning &amp;amp; Deep Learning. Remember I have said “&lt;b&gt;basic&lt;/b&gt;”. You don’t need to be expert in it. And if you have done high school studies good, you most probably have it. So, congrats. You already have base of ML!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While starting, remember on thing. &lt;b&gt;Learn in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Breadth-first_search&quot;&gt;BFS&lt;/a&gt; manner, not in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Depth-first_search&quot;&gt;DFS&lt;/a&gt; manner&lt;/b&gt;. What I want to say is, try to grasp overall idea of each and every concept of ML. Don’t just pick one algorithm and do very deep in it. Remember, in ML, there is no one such algorithm which always gives best result. So, learn basic concept of every algorithm. And apply them to some real world data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the sources. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.coursera.org/learn/machine-learning&quot;&gt;Andrew Ng’s coursera course&lt;/a&gt; is a prefect place to start. The way he teaches ML concepts is very good for beginners. Also, his &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/view_play_list?p=A89DCFA6ADACE599&quot;&gt;Stanford course&lt;/a&gt; is very good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By doing these courses, you will at least have somewhat idea what ML is all about, and &lt;b&gt;how things work&lt;/b&gt;. That’s what our goal was!! Congrats, if you have reached this far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-to-grow-in-ml&quot;&gt;How to grow in ML?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;b&gt;2 main ways&lt;/b&gt; to grow your knowledge in ML. Projects &amp;amp; Competitions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Try to build something which includes some algorithm which you have just learned. It’s not compulsory to select some high level cutting edge project definition. You can even choose to use simplest linear regression in your project. &lt;b&gt;Aim is to implement it and build some real world use case&lt;/b&gt;. While building them, you will face many issues. But that’s perfectly okay!! Find some fix as per your understanding. And move on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second way is Competitions. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kaggle.com/&quot;&gt;Kaggle&lt;/a&gt; is one of the biggest data science community. Take part in running competitions and learn as much as you can. Platforms like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kdnuggets.com/&quot;&gt;KDnuggets&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.analyticsvidhya.com/&quot;&gt;Analytics Vidhya&lt;/a&gt; are also good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Its completely okay if your rank is low in these competitions&lt;/b&gt;. Your aim is not to win millions of dollars by winning these competitions, your aim is to learn something. RANKS REALLY DOESN’T MATTER. You know, in these ML competitions, 1st rank will have let say 0.98598 accuracy and person at 500th rank will have 0.97198 accuracy. Rank difference is very high. But score is nearly same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read and try to understand other people’s view on the same problem by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kaggle.com/kernels&quot;&gt;Kaggle kernels&lt;/a&gt;. Many working professional data scientists share their point of view by kernels. That is &lt;b&gt;the best and fastest way&lt;/b&gt; to capture important things. They have experience and knowledge. See how they think and grow your thinking process that way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;how-to-maintain-the-growth-in-ml&quot;&gt;How to maintain the growth in ML?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is very important. ML is a vast ocean. Even some great researchers doesn’t know &lt;b&gt;all the concepts fully&lt;/b&gt;. And you actually don’t need to digest all concepts. And even one knows all the concepts fully, his/her knowledge will not “full” after a week or two. &lt;mark&gt;Because in ML, every week something new comes&lt;/mark&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep updated yourself by reading &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.arxiv-sanity.com/&quot;&gt;latest research papers&lt;/a&gt;. Reading research papers is an art. You need to read them at least 2–3 times to grasp the very core of it. Try to understand what it is saying. Avoid mathematical formulas at first, if you find it cumbersome. Just grasp the idea. Learn these concepts and apply it in projects and competitions. You can keep up to date yourself in the cutting edge data science research by referring the publications from top tier conferences such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://icml.cc/&quot;&gt;ICML&lt;/a&gt;, and reading blogs such as “&lt;a href=&quot;https://jack-clark.net/&quot;&gt;Import AI&lt;/a&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t know how to know all the things about these top conferences, &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;http://www.guide2research.com/topconf/machine-learning&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; is the best source to know more about each upcoming event in ML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing ML alone can resist your growth. Because you never know what this concept can be viewed this way also. Here comes meet ups and tech-talks. &lt;a href=&quot;https://pydata.org/&quot;&gt;PyData&lt;/a&gt; is one of them. PyData arranges various events and meet ups around the world. Join them if you can. You will definitely learn something new. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pycon.org/&quot;&gt;PyCon&lt;/a&gt; is also good (specially for those who prefer Python as their working language. Which many of use do). Watch some success stories like &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://youtu.be/MOdlp1d0PNA&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rIofV14c0tc&amp;amp;t=100s&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; to encourage your self learning!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, keep visiting &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://towardsdatascience.com/&quot;&gt;Towards Data Science&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://hackernoon.com/&quot;&gt;Hacker Noon&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a rel=&quot;nofollow&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot; href=&quot;https://becominghuman.ai/&quot;&gt;Becoming Human&lt;/a&gt; like websites regularly. All these blog sites have plenty of great blogs written by ML professionals. Also use Twitter wisely. Follow some great professionals there and never be late to catch new things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At last, One important thing. Don’t expect results quickly. I am doing ML for 7 months now. And I don’t know many many concepts of ML (&lt;b&gt;knowing what you don’t know is also an important thing&lt;/b&gt;). You can’t expect to understand and implement all the concepts in half a year.. Things will be understood as the time goes. Don’t compare yourself with anyone. Just be the best version of yourself. Everyone is unique.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And yes, you will need support when things are not going well. So, make a few besties with whom you can share everything including your achievements and sorrows. They will help you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;in-short-if-you-dont-give-up-ml-is-your-cup-of-tea&quot;&gt;&lt;center&gt;In short, If you don't give up, ML is your cup of tea!!&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;👏 👏 You made it till the end!!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;❤️ Have a nice day!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Prashant Kikani</name></author><summary type="html">This little post is about what I have learned from my 7 month ML journey. Hope a newbie like me found something to invest his/her 5 minutes in this.</summary></entry></feed>